Finding Aid for the The Waller Project
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
The Waller Project
undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0486
6.25 Linear Feet
An early report entitled The Waller Project, May 1, 1950 - July 1, 1952 (found in Box 1, Folder l), in outlining the materials of value to the Project, listed A) Interviews, B) Written Memoirs, C) Manuscript Materials, and D) Maps of the City of Nashville. Categories A,B, and C have been followed in arranging the materials here, with the addition of a fourth category of Eleanor Graham's research notes. (No maps of Nashville are included in this collection of Waller materials). A perusal of this early report on the Waller Project is suggested to give one a concise listing of resources available and used by Waller and his associates.
1 Reports on the Waller Project, Source Cards for the Johnson Report, Interviews (taped) Done by Donald Davidson and Carole Shelton, Name Index to Interview Cards.
2 Interview Cards, Narratives of Interviews (typed), Anderson - Moore.
3 Narratives of Interviews (typed), Polk - Wilson, Narratives of Interviews,- drafts with Corrections, Written Memoirs, Manuscript Materials, Related Printed Material, and Duplicates of Narratives of Interviews, Written Memoirs, and Manuscript Materials.
4 Eleanor Graham's Research Notes - including the following: Nashville Chronology 1885 - 1897, Listing of ^nrents, 1890 - l899i Listing of Selected Events 1890 - I899 + Weddings, Notecards - bibliography and Nashville 189O -1899, + Misc. Notecards, and Microfilm of Selected Articles, 1890 - 1899.
- Reports (Box 1)
  The Waller Project, May 1, 1950 - July 1, 1952. Includes a short description of the Project, with an outline of its general objectives, (l)
  Report on Preliminary Survey of Printed Materials Pertinent to The Waller Project, by Arthur M. Johnson, Vanderbilt University, July, 1954. (2)
- Source Cards (Box 1)
  Source Cards for Arthur M. Johnson Report (above).
  Interviews Done by Donald Davidson (with the exception of one by Carole Shelton, noted below taped versions)
  Adams, Adam G. (“Lep”), of Coral Gables, Fla., formerly of Nashville. Interviewed April 30, 1966 at 410 Fairfax Ave., Nashville.
  Frazer, Mrs. George and Mrs. John Reeves, interviewed Feb. 4 1966 at Mrs. Frazer's home, 302 Cornwall Ave., Nashville. (Also present were Mrs. D. Davidson and Prof. Herschel Gower, Vanderbilt University).
  Horn, Stanley F., interviewed Jan. 8, 1966.
  Keyes, Charlie, interviewed Sept. l6, 1965 by Carole Shelton.
  Pope, Lewis S., interviewed Feb. 12, 1966 at his Nashville office in Third National Bank Building.
  Reeves, Mrs. John, see Frazer.
  Stokes, Walter, Jr., interviewed Mar. 29, 1966 at 410 Fairfax Ave., Nashville.
  Williams, Albert, interviewed April 7, 1966 at his home on Murfreesboro Rd.
- Name Index (Box 1)
  - Name Index to Interview Cards.
- Interview Cards (Box 2)
- Narratives of Interviews (Box 2)
  - Anderson, Mrs. J.M., (1) (Box 2)
  - Armistead, George H., Sr., (1) (Box 2)
  - Armistead, Wirt, (1) (Box 2)
  - Benton, Green, (2) (Box 2)
  - Brown, Lytle, (2) (Box 2)
  - Buford, Brown, (2) (Box 2)
  - Chase, Irving, (3) (Box 2)
  - Cullom, Dr. M.M., (3) (Box 2)
  - Daniel, John B., (4) (Box 2)
  - Ewing, Albert, (4) (Box 2)
  - Farrell, Josephine, (5) (Box 2)
  - Fuller, Fred, (5) (Box 2)
  - Handley, Mrs. Avery, (6) (Box 2)
  - Homell, R.B.C., (6) (Box 2)
  - McAlister, Hill, (7) (Box 2)
  - McGill, Mrs. J.T., (7) (Box 2)
  - Mitchell, Charles, (8) (Box 2)
  - Moore, J.W., (8) (Box 2)
- Narratives of Interviews (folder # in parentheses when applicable) (Box 3)
  - Polk, Prudence, (1) (Box 3)
  - Porter, Matilda, (1) (Box 3)
  - Price, Mrs. George, (2) (Box 3)
  - Webb, Mary, (2) (Box 3)
  - West, Dr. Olin, (3) (Box 3)
  - Wilson, Dr. Owen, (3) (Box 3)
- Narratives of Interviews - Drafts with Corrections (Box 3)
  - Armistead, Wirt, (4) (Box 3)
  - Handley, Mrs. Avery, (4) (Box 3)
  - Polk, Prudence, (5) (Box 3)
  - Porter, Matilda, (5) (Box 3)
  - Price, Mrs. George, (5) (Box 3)
- Written Memoirs (Box 3)
  Adams, Mrs. Sue Howell, 50th Anniversary of the Opening of Liberty Hall, Beersheba Springs, June 3, 1922.ttyped copy
  Anderson, J.D., The Making, of a Lawyer - A Biographical Sketch of J .M. Anderson; With Some Facts Relative to Law Practice in Nashville Between 1882 and 1934, Dec, 1940. (typed copy) (7)
  Hickman, Litton, I. Memories of Nashville - Dictated to Mrs. Hickman in the Spring of 1952, and II. The Hickman Family - Dictated to Mrs. Hickman also in the Spring of 1952. typed copy) (7)
  Howell, Alfred T., Recollections of Beersheba, June 28, 1922. (typed copy) (8)
  Howell, Jennie Thompson, Family Talk, 1916 - 1926. (typed copy) '8)
  Justi, Herman, a memoir concerning - unsigned, (typed copy) (8)
  Orr, Mary Thompson (Mrs. Sam), Interview of Mrs. Sam Orr by Mrs. Herbert Weaver at the Home of Mrs. Orr on Franklin Rd. (typed copy) (9)
  - Price Manuscripts (Box 3)
    Brown, J.D., A Dream House Passing (originally in The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, Oct. 2, 1949, and deals with Price's School) Ttyped - original?) (10)
    Price, Elizabeth F., The Founding of the Nashville College for Young Ladies by Dr. George W.F. Price in l880. (typed copy) (10)
    Price, Elizabeth F., The Founding of the Nashville College for Young Ladies by Dr. George W.F. Price. (typed copy) (10)
    Trawick, Arch, An Old Time Drummer Talks about The Grocery Business 1846 - 1946. (Mimeograph read before the Tennessee Historical Society on Jan. 14, 1947) (ll)
    Trawick, Arch, Things Remembered 1890 - 1910. (Mimeograph copy) (ll)
    Vaughn, Stella S, A Half Century at Vanderbilt. (typed copy) (12)
    Vaughn, Stella S., January 29. 1948. (typed copy) (12)
    Vaughn, Stella S., Miss Stella S. Vaughn's Memories of the Vanderbilt Campus 1882 - 1948. (typed copy) (12)
    Vaughn, Susie Kirkman, The Story of My Early Childhood While Living at My Grandfather Woods' Home at Nashville, Tennessee, Under the Care of My Aunt Suaie Woods. (typed copy) (13)
    Wallace, C.B., Papers; I. Birthday Dinner (Paper read at his birthday dinner, Oct. 23, 1949, Maxwell House) (typed copy) (13) II. Paper on old Nashville, read before the Tennessee Historical Society, (typed copy) (14)
    Webb, Mary, Reminiscences, written in August, 1950. (original holograph and typed copies) (14)
    Wilson, Dr. Owen H., A paper written for the family of Dr. Richard Douglas concerning Dr. Douglas' medical training and his role in the development of Vanderbilt Medical School, (typed copy) (15)
    Wilson, Dr. Owen H., Dr. Owen H. Wilson's Notes. (Notes copied from a notebook Dr. Wilson kept of memoirs etc. These notes deal with Wilson's experiences as an undergraduate at Vanderbilt, the early years of the Medical School of Vanderbilt University and the University of Nashville, accounts of Dr. Richard Douglas, reminiscences of Christ Church rectors and wives, early surgery and diseases, Sam Murphy, etc. (typed copy) (15)
    Woods, Mary, Memories, n.d. (typed copy) (l6)
    Woods, Mary, Recollections, n.d. (typed copy) (l6)
- Manuscripts (Box 3)
  - Colonial Dames Record Book, Nov. 1910 - Nov. 1916.; (17) (Box 3)
  - Erskine Club Program, (18) (Box 3)
  - Fall Diary, (19) (Box 3)
  - Hardeman Letters, Description of, (20) (Box 3)
  - The Old Oak Club Galley, (21) (Box 3)
  - Orr, M.T., A Century of Service (Box 3)
  - Page Letters (Incoming to Mr. Thomas Nelson Page; # following name is total # of letters from that person). (Box 3)
  - Baskerville, W.M., (1), March 16, 1889., (23) (Box 3)
  - Binkley, Fay, (Nashville College for Young Ladies - Class of '90), (1), Dec. 22, I887., (23) (Box 3)
  - Brett and Smith, (Mgrs. "Sewanee"), (1), Aug. 13, 1888., (23) (Box 3)
  - Ewing, Randul M., (1), Jan. 8, 1888., (24) (Box 3)
  - Justi, Herman, (1), ca. Jan. 3, 1888, July 20, 1888, (24); Dec. 6, 1888, April 15, 1890, (25) (Box 3)
  - Levine, Mrs. J., (1), plus poem Bumble Bee by Alfred Tennyson Levine) (both n.d.'s)., (25) (Box 3)
  - Page, Fred, (2), July 9, 1888, Oct. 28, 1888., (26) (Box 3)
  - Peck, W.H., (1), Dec. 30, 1888., (26) (Box 3)
  - Price, Elisabeth F., (1), Mar. 12, 1948., (26) (Box 3)
  - Spurr, Lusie Porterfield, (2), Nov. 23, 1888, June 24., (27) (Box 3)
  - Spurr, M.A., (1), June 5, l888., (27) (Box 3)
  - Wardlae, Virginia, (1), Nov. 24, 1888., (27) (Box 3)
  - Warren, J.H., (1), July 26, 1888., (28) (Box 3)
  - Weber, Mrs. Hewie, (1), (n.d.)., (28) (Box 3)
  - One illegible, possibly Clark, Lucy, (1), Oct. 16, 1891., (28) (Box 3)
  - Review Club Books - Minutes, 1895 - 1907., (29) (Box 3)
- Sloan Collection (Box 3)
  I. Howerton Letters, Vol. I. (volume of typewritten copies of Howerton Family letters, 1817 - 1924 (30)
  Photostat copies of letters in Vol I. (31, 32, 33, 34)
  Howerton Letters, Vol. II, A Virginia Gentleman And His Lady -Their Home And Family - Philip and Elizabeth Cabaniss Howerton. (35)
  Misc. family letters and manuscripts.
  Letters
  "Dear Bush" - signed "Aunt Lou", Aug. 31, 1877. (36)
  "My Dear Cousin" - signed "Yannie", July 16, l864. (36)
  "My Dear Cousin" - signed "Maggie Sloan", Aug. 7, 1864. (36)
  "My Dear Mary" - signed "D.M. Tritise" (?), Feb. 26, 1853. (36)
  "Dear Mary" - unsigned, Sept. 18, 1853 - Sept. 20, l853. (37)
  Poen to Mrs. Mary A.M. Howerton - signed Lydia (?). (37)
  Manuscripts
  Original Writing of John Cosby of Halifax, Va., n.d.. (38)
  Statement (Legal) of John E. Dietz, Oct. 1876. (38)
  Statement (Legal), unsigned. (38)
  Verse - The Maniac, by P.W. Howerton, n.d. (38)
- Related Printed Material (39 - 51) (arranged by title) (Box 3)
  "Anniversary Section" - Nashville Gas Company, The Nashville Tennessean, Nov. 4, 1951. (39)
  "Auction Sale Drab End of Romantic Mansion", by Richard Harwood, The Nashville Tennessean, April 8, 1951. (39)
  "Baths to Banking", The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, April 30, 1950. (40)
  "Boyd McNary, Physician and Host", by Nell Savage Mahoney, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, April 1, 1951. (40)
  "Cracker Barrel To Deep Freeze" by Louise Davis, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, June 4, 1950. (40)
  "Do You Remember the Turn of the Century?", see "From Edison...". (43)
  "Dr. Selby's Mansion: The Second Fatherland", by Nell Savage Mahoney, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, May 27, 1951. (41)
  "Dury Portraits of the Past: Patrons and Parlors" by Nell Savage Mahoney, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, March 18, 1951. (41)
  "The End of the Thing" by Margaret Lindsley Warden, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, Jan. 14, 1951. (41)
  "Fabulous Belle Meade", Part I. The Building, Part II. The Blooming, Part III. The Breaking, by Margaret Lindsley Warden, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, April 30, 1950, May 7, 1950, May 14, 1950, respectively. (42)
  "First Contract for Granite Paving of Street" (advertisement of First American National Bank), no newspaper title, n.d.. (42)
  "First Electric Streetcar" (advertisement of First Amer. Natl. Bank), no newspaper title, n.d.. (42)
  "First Time Carnegie Opened its Doors" (advertisement of First Amer. Natl. Bank), no newspaper title, n.d.. (42)
  Firsts in Nashville - A Pictorial History, First Amer. Natl. Bank, 1951, Nashville, Tn. (43)
  "5 Bricklayers Celebrate 50th Year with Union" (photograph and caption), no newspaper title, n.d.. (43)
  "From Edison Cranker to Newest Projectors, Harold Carter's Greeted Every Improvement", The Nashville Tennessean, Feb. 24, 1952. (43)
  "Gothic in Nashville: Pinacles and Spires - I. Christ Church", by Nell Savage Mahoney, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, April 29, 1951- (44)
  "Gothic Revival: Hume School", by Nell Savage Mahoney, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, Nov. 18, 1951. (44)
  "A Haven for Horses", The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, June 11, 1950. (44)
  "Mansion Called Fatherland", by Nell Savage Mahoney, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, May 13, 1951. (44)
  "The McNarys and The Lady from Boston", by Nell Savage Mahoney, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, April 8, 1951. (44)
  Mileposts of a Half Century, by Robert Lee Davis, West End Methodist Church, Anniversary Sunday, Jan. 15, 1950. (45)
  "Mrs. Grundy Approved", by Margaret Lindsley Warren, see "Summer Day Jaunt" (48)
  "Mr. Richmond Remembers", by Nell Savage Mahoney, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, June 4, 1950. (45)
  "Mistress of Cleveland Hall", by Nell Savage Mahoney, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, Nov. 25, 1951« (45)
  "No Spreading Wings", The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, May 7, 1950. (45)
  "Original Ku Klux Klan Robe Marks Eerie Era of Franklin", by Marshall Morgan, The Nashville Banner, Jan. 25, 1951
  "Pastor's Wife Started 'Door of Hope' Home for Girls in 1874", The Nashville Tennessean, Feb. 24, 1952. (46)
  "Portraits of the Past: The Artist", by Nell Savage Mahoney, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, Feb. 25, 1951. (46)
  "Portraits of the Past: The City", by Nell Savage Mahoney, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, March 11, 1951• (46)
  "A Price on His Head", by Josephine Neel Wallen, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, Nov. 4, 1951. (47)
  "The Southern Turf", by Margaret Lindsley Warden, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, May 25, 1952. (47)
  "The Springs of Yore", The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, Nov. 25, 1951. (47)
  "Summer Day Jaunt", by Betsy Rowlett, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, June 17, 1951. (48)
  "A Tennessee Champion", by Margaret Lindsley Warden, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, Aug. 20, 1950. (48)
  "Under the Winged Sun", by Margaret Lindsley Warden, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, April 22, 1951. (49)
  "The University of Nashville, Part I", by Nell Savage Mahoney, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, Dec. 2, 1951. (49)
  "Vanderbilt's Dudley An Athletic Pioneer", by Zipp Newman, The Nashville Banner, Dec. 4, 1950. (49)
  "When Jenny Lind Sang',', by Louise Davis, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, Mar. 25, 1951. (50)
  "When Nashville Was Young", by S.A. Weakley, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, Jan. 20, 1952. (50)
  "Yours to Serve", by John Lipscomb, The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, June 11, 1950. (51)
- Duplicates (52 - 65) (Box 3)
  - Narrative of Interview - Armistead, George, (52) (Box 3)
  - Narrative of Interview - Armistead, Wirt, (53) (Box 3)
  - Narrative of Interview - Brown - Chase, (54) (Box 3)
  - Narrative of Interview - Cullom - Fuller, (55) (Box 3)
  - Narrative of Interview - Homell - McGill, (56) (Box 3)
  - Narrative of Interview - Mitchell - Wilson, (57) (Box 3)
  - Written Memoirs - Adams - Hnderson, (58) (Box 3)
  - Written Memoirs - Howell - Justi, (59) (Box 3)
  - Written Memoirs - Orr - Trawick, (60) (Box 3)
  - Written Memoirs - Vaughn, Stella, (61) (Box 3)
  - Written Memoirs - Vaughn, Susie - Wallace, (62) (Box 3)
  - Written Memoirs - Webb - Wilson, (63) (Box 3)
  - Written Memoirs - Woods, (64) (Box 3)
  - Manuscripts - Fall Diary, (65) (Box 3)
- Eleanor Graham's Research Notes (Box 4)
  - Nashville Chronology, 1885 - 1897, (notebook) (1) (Box 4)
  - Events, Listing of, 1890 - 1892, (2) (Box 4)
  - Events, Listing of, 1893 - 1896, (3) (Box 4)
  - Events, Listing of, 1897 - 1899, (4) (Box 4)
  - Selected Events, Listing of, 1890 - 1899 + Weddings, (5) (Box 4)
  - Notecards, (6-15) (Box 4)
    - Bibliography - Group 1, (6) (Box 4)
    - Bibliography - Group 2, (7) (Box 4)
    - 1890 - 1893, (8) (Box 4)
    - 1894, 1895, Jan. 1896 - Mar. 1896, (9) (Box 4)
    - April 1896 - Aug. 1896, (10) (Box 4)
    - Sept. I896 - Dec. 1896, (ll) (Box 4)
    - Jan. 1897 - Mar. 1897, (12) (Box 4)
    - April 1897 - Dec. 1897, (13) (Box 4)
    - 1888, (14) (Box 4)
    - 1899 + misc. notecards, (Pictures - Sketches to Use, Merrymakers, New Years Day, Biographical Notes) (15) (Box 4)
- Microfilm of Selected Articles 189O - 1899 (Using E. Graham's arrangement by subject)., (16-17) (Box 4)
  E.W. Carmack's letter of resignation from The American, The Daily American, Feb. 12, 1892. (l6)
  Col. Colyar speaks about filing a bill in Chancery Court against The American, The Dally American, May 25, 1890, and The Evening Herald, May 27, l890. (16)
  Comte de Pourtales and bride, Nashville American, April 29, 1896. (16)
  Contest for the Governor's chair - April l895» Governor Turney, Democrat vs. H. Clay Evans, Republican, Nashville Banner and Nashville American, April 1, 1895 - May 3, l895. (16)
  Election of chairman of Women's Boards - Tennessee Centennial, Nashville American and Nashville Banner, Feb. 20, 1896 - May 8, 1896. (17)
  McReynolds runs for Congress, Nashville Banner, Oct. 23, 1896 (17)
  Nashville's New City Hall, Nashville American, Mar. 27, 1898. (17)
  Old turfman's lament (demolition of West Side Race Track), no newspaper title, Nov. 9, 1895. (17)
  Spanish American War - First Tennessee Regiment
  Personnel - Who went to the Philippines
  Homecoming
  Nashville American and Nashville Banner, June 1898 - Nov. 1899. (17)
  Tennessee Central Railway, Nashville American, March 11, 1896. (17)
  Judge Claude Waller presents flag to First Regiment, Nashville American, May 18, I898. (17)